<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<listBibl xmlns:office="urn:oasis:names:tc:opendocument:xmlns:office:1.0"
          xmlns:text="urn:oasis:names:tc:opendocument:xmlns:text:1.0">
   <bibl>General</bibl>
   <bibl>Amt, E., ‘Richard de Lucy, Henry II’s justiciar’,<i>Medieval Prosopography</i>, 9 (1988), 61–87.</bibl>
   <bibl>Attenborough, F.L. (ed.),<i>The Laws of the Earliest English Kings</i>(Cambridge, 1922).</bibl>
   <bibl>Barlow, F., ‘The Constitutions of Clarendon’,<i>Medieval History</i>, 1 (1991), 39–52.</bibl>
   <bibl>Bately, J., ‘John Joscelyn and the laws of the Anglo-Saxon kings’, in Korhammer, M. (ed.),Words, Texts and Manuscripts: Studies in Anglo-Saxon Culture Presented to Helmut Gneuss on the Occasion of his Sixty-Fifth Birthday(Cambridge, 1992), pp. 435–66.</bibl>
   <bibl>Batt, M., ‘The burghal hidage: Axbridge’,<i>Somerset Archaeology and Natural History</i>, 119 (1975), 22–5.</bibl>
   <bibl>Baxter, S., ‘Lordship and justice in late Anglo-Saxon England; the judicial functions of soke and commendation revisited’, in Baxter, S., Karkov, C.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Early Medieval Studies in Memory of Patrick Wormald</i>(Farnham, 2009), pp. 383–419.</bibl>
   <bibl>Boorman, J., ‘<i>Nisi feceris</i>under Henry II’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 24 (2001), 85–96.</bibl>
   <bibl>Boureau, A., ‘Conflicting norms: liturgical procedure and the separation of divine law from human law (England, eleventh century)’,<i>Medieval History Journal</i>, 3 (2000), 17–40.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P., ‘Henry II and the creation of the English common law’, in Harper-Bill, C., and Vincent, N. (eds.),<i>Henry II: New Interpretations</i>(Woodbridge, 2007), pp. 215–41.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P., ‘Legal history’, in Deyermond, A. (ed.),<i>A Century of British Medieval Studies</i>(Oxford, 2007), pp. 181–200.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P., ‘The making of English thirteenth-century legislation: some new evidence’, in Lewis, A. D., Brand, P.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Law in the City: Proceedings of the Seventeenth British Legal History Conference, London, 2005</i>(Dublin, 2007), pp. 42–53.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P., ‘The English difference: the application of bureaucratic norms within a legal system’,<i>Law and History Review</i>, 21 (2003), 383–7.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P., ‘Local custom in the early common law’, in Stafford, P., Nelson, J. L.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.)<i>Law, Laity and Solidarities: Essays in Honour of Susan Reynolds</i>(Manchester, 2001), pp. 150–9.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P., ‘The formation of the English legal system, 1150–1400’, in Schioppa, A. P. (ed.),Legislation and Justice(Oxford, 1997), pp. 103–22.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P.,<i>Origins of the English Legal Profession</i>(Oxford, 1992).</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P.,<i>The Making of the Common Law</i>(London, 1992).</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P., ‘Lordship and distraint in thirteenth-century England’, in Coss, P. R., and Lloyd, S. D. (eds.),Thirteenth-Century England, 3:Proceedings of the Newcastle upon Tyne Conference, 1989(Woodbridge, 1991), pp. 1–24.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brand, P., ‘“Multis vigiliis excogitatam et inventam”: Henry II and the creation of the English common law’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 2 (1990), 197–222.</bibl>
   <bibl>Bridbury, A. R., ‘Seventh-century England in Bede and the early laws’, in Bridbury, A. R. (ed.),The English Economy from Bede to the Reformation(Woodbridge, 1992), pp. 56–85.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brooks, N. P., ‘The Fonthill Letter, Ealdorman Ordlaf and Anglo-Saxon law in practice’,in Baxter, S., Karkov, C.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Early Medieval Studies in Memory of Patrick Wormald</i>(Farnham, 2009), pp. 301–17.</bibl>
   <bibl>Carella, B., ‘The source of the Prologue to the Laws of Alfred’,Peritia: Journal of the Medieval Academy of Ireland, 19, (2005), 91–118.</bibl>
   <bibl>Chibnall, M., ‘“Clio’s legal cosmetics”: law and custom in the work of medieval historians’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 20 (1998), 31–43.</bibl>
   <bibl>Clanchy, M. T., ‘Remembering the past and the good old law’,<i>History</i>, 55 (1970), 165–76.</bibl>
   <bibl>Cooper, A.,<i>Bridges, Law and Power in Medieval England, 700–1400</i>(Woodbridge, 2006).</bibl>
   <bibl>Cooper, A., ‘The rise and fall of the Anglo-Saxon law of the highway’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 12 (2002), 39–69.</bibl>
   <bibl>Cooper, A., ‘The king’s four highways: legal fiction meets fictional law’,<i>Journal of Medieval History</i>, 26 (2000), 351–70.</bibl>
   <bibl>Corner, D., ‘The texts of Henry II’s Assizes’, in Harding, A. (ed.),Law-Making and Law-Makers in British History: Papers Presented to the Edinburgh Legal History Conference, 1977(Royal Historical Society Studies in History, 22,London,1980), pp. 7–20.</bibl>
   <bibl>Dammery, R., ‘Editing the Anglo-Saxon laws: Felix Liebermann and beyond’, in Scragg, D. G., and Szarmach, P. E. (ed.),<i>The Editing of Old English: Papers from the 1990 Manchester Conference</i>(Woodbridge, 1994), pp. 251–61.</bibl>
   <bibl>Davies, R. R., ‘The peoples of Britain and Ireland, 1100–1400, 3: laws and customs’,<i>Transactions of the Royal Historical Society</i>, 6th ser., 6 (1996), 1–23.</bibl>
   <bibl>Doe, N., and Young, J., ‘Administration and law in England from the middle ages to the seventeenth century’,<i>Jahrbuch für europäische Verwaltungsgeschichte</i>, 8 (1996), 1–18.</bibl>
   <bibl>Dohmen, S.,‘Exemplarische Untersuchungen zur Rechtskraft des Privilegs: die gerichtliche Handhabung von Privilegienurkunden in England von König Stephan bis König Johann’,Archiv für Diplomatik, 41 (1996), 33–224.</bibl>
   <bibl>Downer, L. J. (ed.),<i>Leges Henrici Primi</i>(Oxford, 1972).</bibl>
   <bibl>Eska, C. M., ‘Rewarding informers in Cain Domnaig and the Laws of Wihtred’,<i>Cambrian Medieval Celtic Studies</i>, 52 (2006), 1–11.</bibl>
   <bibl>Everard, J., ‘The “Assize of Count Geoffrey” (1185): law and politics in Angevin Brittany’, in Musson, A. (ed.),<i>Expectations of the Law in the Middle Ages</i>(Woodbridge, 2001), pp. 53–65.</bibl>
   <bibl>Fleming, R.,<i>Domesday Book and the Law: Society and Legal Custom in Early Medieval History</i>(Cambridge, 1998).</bibl>
   <bibl>Flower, R., and Smith, H. (eds.),<i>The Parker Chronicle and Laws</i>(Early English Text Society, orig. ser., 208, Oxford, 1941).</bibl>
   <bibl>Green, J. A., ‘“A lasting memorial”: the Charter of Liberties of Henry I’, in Flanagan, M. T., and Green, J. A (eds.),<i>Charters and Charter Scholarship in Britain and Ireland</i>(Basingstoke, 2005), pp. 53–69.</bibl>
   <bibl>Green, J. A.,<i>English Sheriffs to 1154</i>(Public Record Office Handbook, 24,London, 1990).</bibl>
   <bibl>Groot, R. D., ‘The jury of presentment before 1215’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 26 (1982), 1–24.</bibl>
   <bibl>Harris, M., ‘Compensation for injury: a point of contact between early Welsh and Germanic law?’, in Watkin, T. G. (ed.),<i>The Trial of Dic Penderyn and other Essays</i>(Welsh Legal History Society, 2, Cardiff, 2002), pp. 39–76.</bibl>
   <bibl>Harvey, P. D. A., ‘<i>Rectitudines singularum personarum</i>and<i>Gerefa</i>’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 108 (1993), 1–22.</bibl>
   <bibl>Haslam, J., ‘Market and fortress in England in the reign of Offa’,<i>World Archaeology</i>, 19 (1987), 76–93.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hazard, G. C., jr., ‘The early evolution of the common law writs: a sketch’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 6 (1962), 114–22.</bibl>
   <bibl>Helmholz, R. H., ‘The learned laws in “Pollock and Maitland”’,<i>Proceedings of the British Academy</i>, 89 (1996); repr. in Hudson, J. (ed.),The History of English Law: Centenary Essays on ‘Pollock and Maitland’(Oxford, 1996).</bibl>
   <bibl>Holt, J. C., ‘The writs of Henry II’,<i>Proceedings of the British Academy</i>, 89 (1996); repr. in Hudson, J. (ed.),The History of English Law: Centenary Essays on ‘Pollock and Maitland’(Oxford, 1996).</bibl>
   <bibl>Holt, J. C., ‘The Assizes of Henry II: the texts’, in Bullough, A., and Storey, R. L. (eds.),<i>The Study of Medieval Records. Essays in Honour of Kathleen Major</i>(Oxford, 1971).</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘Numbers in manuscripts of Anglo-Saxon law’, in Rumble, A. R. (ed.),<i>Writing and Texts in Anglo-Saxon England</i>(Woodbridge, 2006), pp. 114­­–36.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘Legal and documentary writings’, in Pulsiano, P., and Treharne, E. (eds.),<i>A Companion to Anglo-Saxon Literature</i>(Oxford, 2001), pp. 170–87.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘Palaeographical evidence for the compilation ofTextus Roffensis’,<i>Scriptorium</i>, 55 (2001), 57–79.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J., ‘<i>The Making of English Law</i>and the varieties of legal history’, in Baxter, S., Karkov, C.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Early Medieval Studies in Memory of Patrick Wormald</i>(Farnham, 2009), pp. 421–32.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J., ‘L’écrit, les archives et le droit en Angleterre (IXe–XIIe siècle)’,<i>Revue historique</i>, 637 (2006), 1–35.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J., ‘Maitland and Anglo-Norman law’, in Hudson, J. (ed.),The History of English Law: Centenary Essays on ‘Pollock and Maitland’(Oxford, 1996), pp. 21-46.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J.,<i>The Formation of English Common Law: Law and Society in England from the Norman Conquest to Magna Carta</i>(London, 1996).</bibl>
   <bibl>Hunt, J.,<i>Medieval Justice: Cases and Laws in France, England and Germany, 500–1500</i>(Jefferson, NC, 2004).</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘Norms and legal argument before 1150’, in Lewis, A. D., and Lobban, M. (eds.),<i>Law and History</i>(Current Legal Issues, 6, Oxford, 2004), pp. 41–61.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R.,<i>Rancor and Reconciliation in Medieval England</i>(Ithaca, NY, 2003).</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘Homage and feudalism: a judicious separation’, in Fryde, N., and Monnet, P. (eds.),<i>Die Gegenwart des Feudalismus</i>(Göttingen, 2002), pp. 13–49.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘Henri II comme juriste: eut-il une politique de reforme?’,<i>Cahiers de civilisation médiévale</i>, 37 (1994), 85–89.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘The charter as a source for the early common law’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 12 (1991), 173–89.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘Warranty and good lordship in twelfth century England’,<i>Law and History Review</i>, 5 (1987), 437–503.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘“No register of title”: the Domesday inquest and land adjudication’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 9 (1986), 128–41.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘The action of naifty in the early common law’,<i>Law Quarterly Review</i>, 90 (1974), 326–50.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘The proof of villein status in the common law’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 89 (1974), 721–49.</bibl>
   <bibl>Jenks, S.,‘Die Assisen von Clarendon (1166) und Northampton (1176): eine Neubetrachtung ihres Verhältnisses’,Ius Commune, 21 (1994), 149–68.</bibl>
   <bibl>Joüon des Longrais, F.,<i>Henry II and his Justiciars: had they a Political Plan in their Reforms about Seisin?</i>(Limoges, 1962).</bibl>
   <bibl>Joüon des Longrais, F., ‘Le statut de la femme en Angleterre dans le droit commun médiéval’,<i>Receuils Société Jean Bodin</i>, 12 (1962), 135–241.</bibl>
   <bibl>Joüon des Longrais, F., ‘La portée politique des réformes d'Henri II en matière de saisine’,<i>Revue historique de droit français et étranger</i>, 4th ser., 3 (1936), 540–71.</bibl>
   <bibl>Keeton, G. W.,<i>The Norman Conquest and the Common Law</i>(London, 1966).</bibl>
   <bibl>Kemp, B. R., ‘Exchequer and Bench in the later twelfth century – separate or identical tribunals?’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 88 (1973), 559–73.</bibl>
   <bibl>Keynes, S., ‘Royal government and the written word in late Anglo-Saxon England’, in McKitterick, R. (ed.),The Uses of Literacy in Early Mediaeval Europe(Cambridge, 1990), pp. 226–57.</bibl>
   <bibl>Knowles, D.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.), ‘Henry II’s supplement to the Constitutions of Clarendon’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 87 (1972), 757–71.</bibl>
   <bibl>Liebermann, F., ‘Ist Lambardes Text der Gesetze Athelstans neuzeitliche Fälschung?’,Beiblatt zur Anglia, 35 (1924), 214–18; 36 (1925), 345–7.</bibl>
   <bibl>Liebermann, F.,Die Gesetze der Angelsachsen(3 vols., Halle, 1903–16).</bibl>
   <bibl>Liebermann, F.,‘Gerefa’,Anglia: Zeitschrift für Englische Philologie, 9 (1886), 251–66.</bibl>
   <bibl>Loengard, J. S., ‘Lords’ rights and neighbors’ nuisances: mills and medieval English law’, in Walton, S. A. (ed.),<i>Wind and Water in the Middle Ages: Fluid Technologies from Antiquity to the Renaissance</i>(Medieval and Renaissance Texts and Studies, 322, Tempe, AZ, 2006).</bibl>
   <bibl>Loomis, D. B., ‘<i>Regnum</i>and<i>sacerdotium</i>in the early eleventh century’, in Clemoes, P., and Hughes, K. (eds.),<i>England before the Conquest: Studies in Primary Sources Presented to Dorothy Whitelock</i>(Cambridge, 1971), pp. 129–45.</bibl>
   <bibl>Loyn, H. R., ‘De iure domini regis: a comment on royal authority in eleventh-century England’, in Hicks, C. (ed.),England in the Eleventh Century: Proceedings of the 1990 Harlaxton Symposium(Harlaxton Medieval Studies, 2, Stamford, 1992), pp. 17–24.</bibl>
   <bibl>McLeod, N. D. B., ‘Parallel and paradox: compensation in the legal systems of Celtic Ireland and Anglo-Saxon England’,<i>Studia Celtica</i>, 16 (1983 for 1981).</bibl>
   <bibl>Macnair, M., ‘Vicinage and the antecedents of the jury’,<i>Law and History Review</i>, 17 (1999), 537–90.</bibl>
   <bibl>Milsom, S. F. C., ‘The origin of prerogative wardship’, in Garnett, G., and Hudson, J. (eds.),Law and Government in Medieval England and Normandy: Essays in Honour of Sir James Holt(Cambridge, 1994), pp. 223–44.</bibl>
   <bibl>Mooers, S. L., ‘A re-evaluation of royal justice under Henry I of England (pipe roll 1130)’,<i>American Historical Review</i>, 93 (1988), 340–58.</bibl>
   <bibl>Nelson, J. L., ‘England and the continent in the ninth century III: rights and rituals’,<i>Transactions of the Royal Historical Society</i>, 6th ser., 14 (2004), 1–24.</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Brien, B.,<i>God’s Peace and King’s Peace: the Laws of Edward the Confessor</i>(Philadelphia, PA, 1999).</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Brien, B., ‘The Becket conflict and the invention of the myth of<i>lex non scripta</i>’, in Bush, J. A., and Wijffels, A. A. (eds.),Learning the Law: Teaching and the Transmission of Law in England, 1150–1900(London, 1999), pp. 1–16.</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Brien, B., ‘Forgery and the literacy of the early common law’,<i>Albion</i>, 27 (1995), 1–18.</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Keeffe, K., ‘Body and law in late Anglo-Saxon England’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 27 (1998), 209–32.</bibl>
   <bibl>Oleson, T. J.,<i>The</i>
      <i>Witenagemot in the Reign of Edward the Confessor</i>(London, 1955).</bibl>
   <bibl>Oliver, E., ‘Royal and ecclesiastical law in seventh-century Kent’, in Baxter, S., Karkov, C.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Early Medieval Studies in Memory of Patrick Wormald</i>(Farnham, 2009), pp. 97–112.</bibl>
   <bibl>Oliver, L.,<i>The Beginnings of English Law</i>(Toronto Medieval Texts and Translations, 14, Toronto, CO, 2002).</bibl>
   <bibl>Page, R. I.,‘Gerefa: some problems of meaning’, in Bammesberger, A. (ed.),Problems of Old English Lexicography: Studies in Memory of Angus Cameron(Regensberg, 1985), 211–28.</bibl>
   <bibl>Palmer, R. C., ‘England: law, society and the state’, in Rigby, S. H. (ed.),<i>A Companion to Britain in the Later Middle Ages</i>(Oxford, 2003), pp. 242–60.</bibl>
   <bibl>Pantos, A., ‘“On the edge of things”: the boundary location of Anglo-Saxon assembly sites’,Anglo-Saxon Studies in Archaeology and History, 12 (2003), 38–49.</bibl>
   <bibl>Pollock, F., and Maitland, F. W.,<i>History of English Law before the Time of Edward I</i>(2nd edn., Cambridge, 1968).</bibl>
   <bibl>Poole, R. G., ‘The textile inventory in the Old EnglishGerefa’,Review of English Studies,new ser., 40 (1989), 469–78.</bibl>
   <bibl>Pugh, R. B., ‘The king’s prisons before 1250’,<i>Transactions of the Royal Historical Society</i>, 5th ser., 5 (1955), 1–22.</bibl>
   <bibl>Rabin, A., ‘Old English<i>forespeca</i>and the role of the advocate in Anglo-Saxon law’,<i>Mediaeval Studies</i>, 69 (2007), 223–54.</bibl>
   <bibl>Reedy, W. T., ‘The origins of the general eyre in the reign of Henry I’,<i>Speculum</i>, 41 (1966), 688–724.</bibl>
   <bibl>Richards, M. P., ‘The body as text in early Anglo-Saxon Law’, in Withers, B. C., and Wilcox, J. (eds.),<i>Naked before God: Uncovering the Body in Anglo-Saxon England</i>(Medieval European Studies, 3, Morgantown, WV, 2003), pp. 97–115.</bibl>
   <bibl>Richards, M. P., ‘Anglo-Saxonism in the Old English laws’, in Frantzen, A. J., and Niles, J. D. (eds.),<i>Anglo-Saxonism and the Construction of Social Identity</i>(Gainesville, FL, 1997), pp. 40–59.</bibl>
   <bibl>Richards, M. P., ‘Elements of a written standard in the Old English Laws’, in Trahern, J. B. (ed.),<i>Standardizing English: Essays in the History of Language Change in Honor of John Hurt Fisher</i>(Knoxville, TN, 1989), pp. 1–22.</bibl>
   <bibl>Richards, M. P., ‘The manuscript contexts of the Old English laws: tradition and innovation’, in Szarmach, P. E. (ed.),<i>Studies in Earlier Old English Prose</i>(Albany,NY, 1986), pp. 171–92.</bibl>
   <bibl>Richardson, H. G. and Sayles, G. O.,<i>Law and Legislation from Æthelberht to Magna Carta</i>(Edinburgh, 1966).</bibl>
   <bibl>Robertson, A. J. (ed.),<i>The Laws of the Kings of England from Edmund to Henry I</i>(Cambridge, 1925).</bibl>
   <bibl>Rubin, S., ‘Medical attention in Anglo-Saxon law: a statute sequence reconsidered’,<i>Medieval Life</i>, 6 (1997), 3–6.</bibl>
   <bibl>Rubin, S., ‘The Bot, or composition in Anglo-Saxon law: a reassessment’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 17 (1996), 144–54.</bibl>
   <bibl>Seebohm, F.,<i>Tribal Custom in Anglo-Saxon Law</i>(London, 1902).</bibl>
   <bibl>Sellar, W. D. H., ‘The common law of Scotland and the common law of England’, in Davies, R. R. (ed.),The British Isles, 1100-1500: Comparisons, Contrasts and Connections(Edinburgh, 1988), pp. 82–99.</bibl>
   <bibl>Sharpe, R., ‘The prefaces of<i>Quadripartitus</i>’, in Garnett, G., and Hudson, J. (eds.),Law and Government in Medieval England and Normandy: Essays in Honour of Sir James Holt(Cambridge, 1994), pp. 148–72.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stacey, R. C., ‘Law and order in the very old west: England and Ireland in the early middle ages’, in Hudson, B. T., and Ziegler, V. (eds.),Crossed Paths: Methodological Approaches to the Celtic Aspect of the European Middle Ages(Lanham, MD, 1991), pp. 39–60.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stack, G., ‘A lost law of Henry II: the Assize of Oxford and monetary reform’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 16 (2006 for 2005), 95–103.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stafford,P.,et al.(eds.),Law, Laity, and Solidarities<i>: Essays in Honour of Susan Reynolds</i>(Manchester, 2001).</bibl>
   <bibl>Stanley, E. G., ‘On the Laws of King Alfred: the end of the preface and the beginning of the Laws’, in Roberts, J.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),Alfred the Wise: Studies in Honour of Janet Bately on the Occasion of her Sixty-Fifth Birthday(Cambridge, 1997), pp. 211–22.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stenton, D. M.,<i>English Justice between the Norman Conquest and the Great Charter, 1066–1215</i>, The Jayne Lectures 1963 (London, 1965).</bibl>
   <bibl>Stenton, D. M., ‘King John and the courts of justice’,<i>Proceedings of the British Academy</i>, 44 (1959), 103–28.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stoljar, S. J., ‘Of socage and socmen’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 6 (1985), 33–48.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘Twelfth and thirteenth-century English law and government: suggestions for prosopographical approaches’,<i>Medieval Prosopography</i>, 3 (1982), 21–34.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘The origins of Common Pleas and King’s Bench’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 21 (1977), 238–54.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘The judges of King John: their background and training’,<i>Speculum</i>, 51 (1976), 447–61.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘The origins of the medieval English jury: Frankish, English, or Scandinavian?’,<i>Journal of British Studies</i>, 7 (1968), 1–10.</bibl>
   <bibl>Ullmann, W., ‘Law and the medieval historian’, in<i>XIe Congrès International des Sciences Historiques, Stockholm, 21–28 Août</i>(Stockholm, 1960), pp. 34–74.</bibl>
   <bibl>Van Caenegem, R. C.,<i>Legal History: a European Perspective</i>(London, 1991).</bibl>
   <bibl>Vogt, H., and Münster-Swendsen,M. (eds.),Law and Learning in the Middle Ages<i>: Proceedings of the Second Carlsberg Academy Conference on Medieval Legal History 2005</i>(Copenhagen, 2006).</bibl>
   <bibl>Walker, S. S., ‘The Action of Waste in the early common law’, in Baker, J. H. (ed.)Legal Records and the Historian: Papers Presented to the Cambridge Legal History Conference, 7–10 July 1975, and in Lincoln’s Inn Old Hall on 3 June 1974(London,1978), pp. 185–206.</bibl>
   <bibl>Warren, W. L.,<i>The Governance of Norman and Angevin England, 1086–1272</i>(Stanford, CA,1987).</bibl>
   <bibl>West, F.,<i>The Justiciarship in England, 1066–1232</i>(Cambridge, 1966).</bibl>
   <bibl>White, S. D., ‘The ambiguity of treason in Anglo-Norman-French law,<i>c</i>.1150–<i>c</i>.1250’, in Karras, R. M., Kaye, J., and Matter, E. A. (eds.),<i>Law and the Illicit in Medieval Europe</i>(Philadelphia, PA, 2008), pp. 89–102.</bibl>
   <bibl>White, S. D., ‘Kinship and lordship in early medieval England: the story of Sigeberht, Cynewulf and Cyneheard’,<i>Viator</i>, 20 (1989), 1–18.</bibl>
   <bibl>Whitelock, D.,<i>History, Law and Literature in 10th–11th Century England</i>(London, 1981).</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P.,<i>The First Code of English Law</i>(Canterbury, 2005).</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P.,<i>The Making of English Law: King Alfred to the Twelfth Century</i>, 1:<i>Legislation and its Limits</i>(Oxford, 1999).</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘Maitland and Anglo-Saxon law: beyond Domesday Book’,<i>Proceedings of the British Academy</i>, 89 (1996), 1–20.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘Lordship and justice in the Early English Kingdom: Oswaldslow revisited’, in Davies, W., and Fouracre, P. (eds.),Property and Power in the Early Middle Ages(Cambridge, 1995), 114–36.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘<i>Quadripartitus</i>’, in Garnett, G., and Hudson, J. (eds.),Law and Government in Medieval England and Normandy: Essays in Honour of Sir James Holt(Cambridge, 1994), pp. 111–47.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘<i>Laga Eadwardi</i>: the<i>Textus Roffensis</i>and its context’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 17 (1994), 243–66.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘In search of King Offa’s Law-Code’, in Wood, I. N., and Lund, N. (eds.),People and Places in Northern Europe, 500–1600: Essays in Honour of Peter Hayes Sawyer(Woodbridge, 1991), pp. 25–45.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘<i>Lex scripta</i>and<i>verbum regis</i>: legislation and Germanic kingship from Euric to Cnut’, in Sawyer, P. H., and Wood, I. N. (eds.),Early Medieval Kingship(Leeds, 1977), pp. 105–38.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Aethelberht</bibl>
   <bibl>Chaney, W. A., ‘Aethelberht’s Code and the King’s Number’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 6 (1962), 151–77.</bibl>
   <bibl>Fell, C. E., ‘An appendix to Carol Hough’s article “A reappraisal of Æthelberht 84”’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 37 (1993), 7–8.</bibl>
   <bibl>Gendre, R., ‘Le leggi di Aethelberht: “iuxta exempla Romanoru” e “iuxta consuetudines Germanorum”’, in Lazzari, L. (ed.),<i>Testi giuridici germanici</i>(Potenza, 1992), pp. 7–21.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘Two Kentish laws concerning women: a new reading of Æthelberht 73 and 74’,<i>Anglia: Zeitschrift für englische Philologie</i>, 119 (2001), 554–78.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘The early Kentish “divorce laws”: a reconsideration of Æthelberht, chs. 79 and 80’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 23 (1994), 19–34.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘A reappraisal of Æthelberht 84’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 37 (1993), 1–6.</bibl>
   <bibl>Jurasinski, S., ‘Germanism, slapping and the cultural contexts of Æthelberht’s Code: a reconsideration of chapters 56–58’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 18 (2007 for 2006), 51–71.</bibl>
   <bibl>Jurasinski, S., ‘The continental origins of Æthelberht’s Code’,<i>Philological Quarterly</i>, 80 (2001), 1–15.</bibl>
   <bibl>Rubin, S., ‘Æthelberht 36. A medico-linguistical discussion on the word<i>Hion</i>’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 39 (1995), 19–25.</bibl>
   <bibl>Simpson, A. W. B., ‘The Laws of Ethelbert’, in Green, M. S.,<i>et al.</i>(ed.),On the Laws and Customs of England: Essays in Honor of Samuel E. Thorne(Chapel Hill, NC, 1981), pp. 3–17.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Aethelred II</bibl>
   <bibl>Gillingham, J., ‘“The most precious jewel in the English crown”: levels of Danegeld and Heregeld in the early eleventh century’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 104 (1989), 373–84.</bibl>
   <bibl>Karaus, A.,Die Sprache der Gesetze des Königs Aethelred(Berlin,1901).</bibl>
   <bibl>Keynes, S., ‘Crime and punishment in the reign of King Æthelred the Unready’, in Wood, I. N., and Lund, N. (eds.),People and Places in Northern Europe, 500–1600: Essays in Honour of Peter Hayes Sawyer(Woodbridge, 1991), pp. 67–81.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘Archbishop Wulfstan and the homiletic element in the Laws of Æthelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 107 (1992), 565–86.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘Danegeld and Heregeld once more’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 105 (1990), 951–61.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘“Those stories look true”: levels of taxation in the reigns of Aethelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 104 (1989), 385–406.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘The collection of Danegeld and Heregeld in the reigns of Aethelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 99 (1984), 721–38.</bibl>
   <bibl>Neff, C., ‘Scandinavian elements in the Wantage Code of Æthelred II’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 10 (1989), 285–316.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P.,‘Æthelred the Lawmaker’, in Hill, D. (ed.),Ethelred the Unready: Papers from the Millenary Conference(BAR British ser., 59, Oxford, 1978), pp. 47–80.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Canon and Roman law</bibl>
   <bibl>Brasington, B. C., ‘Canon law in the Leges Henrici Primi’,Zeitschrift der Savigny-Stiftung für Rechtsgeschichte. Kanonistische Abteilung, 123 (2006), 288–305.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brundage, J. A., ‘The monk as lawyer’,<i>The Jurist</i>, 39 (1979), 423–36.</bibl>
   <bibl>Brundage, J. A.,The Profession and Practice of Medieval Canon Law(Aldershot, 2004).</bibl>
   <bibl>Cross, J. E., and Hamer, A. (eds.),<i>Wulfstan’s Canon Law Collection</i>(Anglo-Saxon Texts, 1, Woodbridge, 1999).</bibl>
   <bibl>De Zulueta, F., and Stein, P. G. (eds.),<i>The Teaching of Roman Law in England around 1200</i>(Selden Society supplementary ser., 8, London, 1990).</bibl>
   <bibl>Jones, M. E., ‘The legacy of Roman law in post-Roman Britain’, in Mathisen, R. W. (ed.),<i>Law, Society, and Authority in Late Antiquity</i>(Oxford, 2001), pp. 52–67.</bibl>
   <bibl>Kuttner, S., and Rathbone E., ‘Anglo-Norman canonists of the twelfth century’,<i>Traditio</i>, 7 (1949–51), 279–358.</bibl>
   <bibl>Rathbone, E., ‘Roman law in the Anglo-Norman realm’, in Forchielli, J., and Stickler, A. M. (eds.),<i>Studia Gratiana post octava decreti saecularia auctore consilio commemorationi Gratianae Instruendae edita</i>(Collectanea historiae juris canonici, 11, Rome, 1967), pp. 253–71.</bibl>
   <bibl>Richardson, H. G., ‘The marriage of Isabelle of Angoulême: a problem of canon law’, in Forchielli, J., and Stickler, A. M. (eds.),<i>Studia Gratiana post octava decreti saecularia auctore consilio commemorationi Gratianae Instruendae edita</i>, Collectanea historiae juris canonici, 11 (Rome, 1967), 397–423.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stein, P. G., ‘Custom in Roman and medieval civil law’,<i>Continuity and Change</i>, 10 (1995), 337–44.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘Roman law in England before the time of Bracton’,Journal of British Studies, 15 (1975), 1–25.</bibl>
   <bibl>Winkler, J. F., ‘Roman law in Anglo-Saxon England’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 13 (1992), 101–27.</bibl>
   <bibl>Worby, S., ‘Kinship: the canon law and the common law in thirteenth-century England’,<i>Historical Research</i>, 80 (2007), 443–68.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Church and learning</bibl>
   <bibl>Boureau, A., ‘Conflicting norms: liturgical procedure and the separation of divine law from human law (England, eleventh century)’,<i>Medieval History Journal</i>, 3 (2000), 17–40.</bibl>
   <bibl>Cheney, M., ‘“Possessio/proprietas” in ecclesiastical courts in mid twelfth-century England’, in Garnett, G., and Hudson, J. (eds.),Law and Government in Medieval England and Normandy: Essays in Honour of Sir James Holt(Cambridge, 1994), pp. 245–54.</bibl>
   <bibl>Davies, D. S.,<i>The Bible in English Law</i>, Lucien Wolf Memorial Lecture, 16 (London,1954).</bibl>
   <bibl>Douglas, A. W., ‘Tenure in<i>elemosina</i>: origins and establishment in twelfth-century England’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 24 (1980), 95–132.</bibl>
   <bibl>Douglas, A. W., ‘Frankalmoin and the jurisdictional immunity: Maitland revisited’,<i>Speculum</i>, 53 (1978), 26–48.</bibl>
   <bibl>Evans, G. R.,Law and Theology in the Middle Ages(London, 2002).</bibl>
   <bibl>Frantzen, A. J., ‘The tradition of penitentials in Anglo-Saxon England’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 11 (1983), 23–56.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘Penitential literature and secular law in Anglo-Saxon England’,<i>Anglo-Saxon Studies in Archaeology &amp; History</i>, 11 (2000), 133–42.</bibl>
   <bibl>Keynes, S., ‘Royal government and the written word in late Anglo-Saxon England’, in McKitterick, R. (ed.),The Uses of Literacy in Early Mediaeval Europe(Cambridge, 1990), pp. 226–57.</bibl>
   <bibl>Mayr-Harting, H., ‘The role of Benedictine abbeys in the development of Oxford as a centre of legal learning’, in Wansbrough, H., and Marett-Todd, A. (eds.),Benedictines in Oxford(London, 1997), pp. 11–19, 279–80.</bibl>
   <bibl>Meaney, A. L., ‘Old English legal and penitential penalties for “heathenism”’, in Keynes, S., and Smyth, A. P. (eds.),<i>Anglo-Saxons: Studies Presented to Cyril Roy Hart</i>(Dublin, 2006), pp. 127–58.</bibl>
   <bibl>Nelson, J. L., ‘Liturgy or law: misconceived alternatives?’, in Baxter, S., Karkov, C.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Early Medieval Studies in Memory of Patrick Wormald</i>(Farnham, 2009), pp. 433–47.</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Brien, B., ‘The Becket conflict and the invention of the myth of<i>lex non scripta</i>’, in Bush, J. A., and Wijffels, A. A. (eds.),Learning the Law: Teaching and the Transmission of Law in England, 1150–1900(London, 1999), pp. 1–16.</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Brien, B., ‘Forgery and the literacy of the early common law’,<i>Albion</i>, 27 (1995), 1–18.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stanley, E. G., ‘Wulfstan and Ælfric: “the true difference between the law and the gospel”’, in Townend, M. (ed.),<i>Wulfstan, Archbishop of York: the Proceedings of the Second Alcuin Conference</i>(Studies in the Early Middle Ages, 10, Turnhout, 2004), pp. 429–41.</bibl>
   <bibl>Taliadoros, J., ‘Law and theology in Gilbert of Foliot’s correspondence’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 16 (2006), 77–94.</bibl>
   <bibl>Taliadoros, J.,<i>Law and Theology in Twelfth-Century England: the Works of Master Vacarius (c.1115/1120–c.1200)</i>(Disputatio, 10, Turnhout, 2006).</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘Clerical judges in English secular courts: the ideal vs. the reality’,<i>Medievalia et Humanistica</i>, new ser., 3 (1972).</bibl>
   <bibl>Watt, J. A., ‘The Jews, the law, and the Church: the concept of Jewish serfdom in thirteenth-century England’, in Wood, D. (ed.),The Church and Sovereignty, c.590–1918: Essays in Honour of Michael Wilks(Studies in Church History, Subsidia, 9, Oxford, 1991), pp. 153–72.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Cnut</bibl>
   <bibl>Kennedy, A. G., ‘Cnut’s Law Code of 1018’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 11 (1983), 57–81.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘Archbishop Wulfstan and the homiletic element in the Laws of Æthelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 107 (1992), 565–86.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘“Those stories look true”: levels of taxation in the reigns of Aethelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 104 (1989), 385–406.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘The collection of Danegeld and Heregeld in the reigns of Aethelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 99 (1984), 721–38.</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Brien, B., ‘The<i>Instituta Cnuti</i>and the translation of English law’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 25 (2003), 177–97.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stafford, P., ‘The laws of Cnut and the history of Anglo-Saxon royal promises’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 10 (1982), 173–90.</bibl>
   <bibl>Whitelock, D., ‘Wulfstan’s authorship of Cnut’s Laws’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 70 (1955), 72–85.</bibl>
   <bibl>Whitelock, D., ‘Wulfstan and the Laws of Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 63 (1948), 433–52.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P.,‘<i>Lex scripta</i>and<i>verbum regis</i>: legislation and Germanic kingship from Euric to Cnut’, in Sawyer,P. H.,and Wood, I. N. (eds.),Early Medieval Kingship(Leeds, 1977), pp. 105–38.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Courts</bibl>
   <bibl>Coss, P. R., ‘Knighthood and the early thirteenth-century county court’, in Coss, P. R., and Lloyd , S. D. (eds.),Thirteenth century England, 2:Proceedings of the Newcastle upon Tyne Conference 1987(Woodbridge, 1988), pp. 45–57.</bibl>
   <bibl>Oleson, T. J.,<i>The</i>
      <i>Witenagemot in the Reign of Edward the Confessor</i>(London, 1955).</bibl>
   <bibl>Pantos, A., ‘“On the edge of things”: the boundary location of Anglo-Saxon assembly sites’,Anglo-Saxon Studies in Archaeology and History,12 (2003), 38–49.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘The royal courts treat disseizin by the king: John and Henry III, 1199–1240’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 12 (1968), 1–18.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘The medieval English royal courts, problem of their origins’,<i>The Historian</i>, 27 (1965), 471–97.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Crime</bibl>
   <bibl>Beckerman, J. S., ‘Adding insult to iniuria: affronts to honour and the origins of trespass’, in Green, M. S. A.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),On the Laws and Customs of England: Essays in Honor of Samuel E. Thorne(Chapel Hill, NC, 1981), pp. 159–81.</bibl>
   <bibl>Bonser, W., ‘Anglo-Saxon laws and charms relating to theft’,<i>Folk-Lore</i>, 57 (1946), 7–11.</bibl>
   <bibl>Carson, H. L., ‘A sketch of the early development of English criminal law as displayed in Anglo-Saxon law’,<i>American Bar Association Journal</i>, 2 (1916), 135–51.</bibl>
   <bibl>Colman, R. V., ‘<i>Hamsocn</i>: its meaning and significance in early English law’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 25 (1981), 95–110.</bibl>
   <bibl>Groot, R. D., ‘The crime of rape temp. Richard I and John’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 9 (1988), 324–34.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hollis, S.,‘Old English “cattle-theft charms”: manuscript contexts and social uses’,Anglia: Zeitschrift für Englische Philologie, 115 (1997), 139–64.</bibl>
   <bibl>Horner, S., ‘The language of rape in Old English literature and law: views from the Anglo-Saxon(ist)s’, in Pasternack, C.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Sex and Sexuality in Anglo-Saxon England: Essays in Memory of Daniel Gillmore</i>(Medieval and Renaissance Texts and Studies, 277, Tempe, AZ, 2004), pp. 149–81.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J., ‘Kings and crimes: ideology and practice in the tenth and twelfth centuries’, in Chassaigne, P., and Genêt, J.-P. (eds.),<i>Droit et société en France et en Grande-Bretagne (XIIe–XXe siècles)</i>(Collection internationale, 71, Paris, 2003).</bibl>
   <bibl>Kerr, M. H, ‘Angevin reform of the appeal of felony’,<i>Law and History Review</i>, 13 (1995), 351–91.</bibl>
   <bibl>Keynes, S., ‘Crime and punishment in the reign of King Æthelred the Unready’, in Wood, I. N., and Lund, N. (eds.),People and Places in Northern Europe, 500–1600: Essays in Honour of Peter Hayes Sawyer(Woodbridge, 1991), pp. 67–81.</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Brien, B., ‘From<i>morðor</i>to<i>murdrum</i>: the pre-Conquest origin and Norman revival of the murder fine’,<i>Speculum</i>, 71 (1996), 321–57.</bibl>
   <bibl>Riggs, C. H.,<i>Criminal Asylum in Anglo-Saxon Law</i>(University of Florida Monographs, Social Sciences, 18, Gainesville, FL, 1963).</bibl>
   <bibl>Van Caenegem, R. C., ‘Public prosecution of crime in twelfth-century England’, in Brooke, C.N.L.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),Churchand Government in the Middle Ages: Essays Presented to C. R. Cheney(Cambridge, 1976), pp. 41–76.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>The Danelaw</bibl>
   <bibl>Arngart, O. S., ‘Some aspects of the relation between the English and the Danish element in the Danelaw’,<i>Studia Neophilologica</i>, 20 (1948), 73–87.</bibl>
   <bibl>Fellows Jensen, G., ‘Of Danes – and thanes – and Domesday Book’, in Wood, I. N., and Lund, N. (eds.),People and Places in Northern Europe, 500–1600: Essays in Honour of Peter Hayes Sawyer(Woodbridge, 1991), pp. 107–21.</bibl>
   <bibl>Fenger, O., ‘The Danelaw and the Danish law: Anglo-Scandinavian legal relations during the Viking period’,<i>Scandinavian Studies in Law</i>, 16 (1972), 83–96.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hart, C. J. R., ‘The hide, the carucate and the ploughland’, in Hart, C. J. R. (ed.),The Danelaw(London, 1992), pp. 289–335.</bibl>
   <bibl>Kristensen, A. K. G., ‘Danelaw institutions and Danish society in the Viking age: sochemanni, liberi homines and Königsfreie’,<i>Medieval Scandinavia</i>, 8 (1975), 27–85.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lauring, P.,Danelagen: Danmark i England(Copenhagen, 1957).</bibl>
   <bibl>Lund, N., ‘King Edgar and the Danelaw’,<i>Medieval Scandinavia</i>, 9 (1976), 181–95.</bibl>
   <bibl>Pelteret, D., ‘Slavery in the Danelaw’, in Samson, R. (ed.),<i>Social Approaches to Viking Studies</i>(Glasgow,1991), pp. 179–88.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Disputes and dispute settlement</bibl>
   <bibl>Baines, A. H. J., ‘Wynflaed v. Leofwine: a Datchet lawsuit of 990’,<i>Records of Buckinghamshire</i>, 32 (1991 for 1990), 63–75.</bibl>
   <bibl>Bates, D., ‘The land pleas of William I’s reign: Penenden Heath revisited’,<i>Bulletin of the Institute of Historical Research</i>, 51 (1978), 1–19.</bibl>
   <bibl>Birrell, J., ‘Common rights in the medieval forest: disputes and conflicts in the thirteenth century’,<i>Past &amp; Present</i>, 117 (1987), 22–49.</bibl>
   <bibl>Clanchy, M. T., ‘Law and love in the middle ages’, in Bossy, J.A. (ed.),<i>Disputes and Settlements: Law and Human Relations in the West</i>(Cambridge, 1983), pp. 47–67.</bibl>
   <bibl>Corral, F. L., ‘Alfonso VIII of Castile’s judicial process at the court of Henry II of England: an effective and valid arbitration?’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 50 (2006), 22–42.</bibl>
   <bibl>Engdahl, D. E., ‘English marriage conflicts law before the time of Bracton’,<i>American Journal of Comparative Law</i>, 15 (1966–7), 109–35.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J., ‘La interpretación de disputas y resoluciones: el caso inglés, 1066–1135’,<i>Hispania; revista española de historia</i>, 57 (1997), 885–916.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R.,<i>Rancor and Reconciliation in Medieval England</i>(Ithaca, NY, 2003).</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘Feud and the state in late Anglo-Saxon England’,<i>Journal of British Studies</i>, 40 (2001), 1–43.</bibl>
   <bibl>Kennedy, A. G., ‘Law and litigation in the<i>Libellus Æthelwoldi episcopi</i>’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 24 (1995), 131–83.</bibl>
   <bibl>Kennedy, A. G., ‘Disputes about<i>bocland</i>: the forum for their adjudication’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 14 (1985), 175–95.</bibl>
   <bibl>King, E., ‘Dispute settlement in Anglo-Norman England’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 14 (1991), 115–30.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Miller, W. I., ‘Choosing the avenger: some aspects of the blood-feud in medieval Iceland and England’,<i>Law and History Review</i>, 1 (1983), 159–204.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Taylor, N. L., ‘Kin and the courts: testimony of kinship in lawsuits of Angevin England’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 15 (2004), 55–72.</bibl>
   <bibl>Van Caenegem, R. C.,<i>English Lawsuits from William I to Richard I</i>(2 vols., Selden Society, 106–7, London, 1990–1).</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘Domesday lawsuits: a provisional list and preliminary comment’, in Hicks, C. (ed.),England in the Eleventh Century: Proceedings of the 1990 Harlaxton Symposium(Harlaxton Medieval Studies, 2, Stamford, 1992), pp. 61–102).</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘A handlist of Anglo-Saxon lawsuits’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 17 (1988), 247–81.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘Charters, law and the settlement of disputes in Anglo-Saxon England’, in Davies, W., and Fouracre, P. (eds.),<i>The Settlement of Disputes in Early Medieval Europe</i>(Cambridge, 1986), pp. 149–68.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Ethnicity</bibl>
   <bibl>Alexander, L. M., ‘The legal status of the native Britons in late seventh-century Wessex as reflected by the Law Code of Ine’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 7 (1995), 31–8.</bibl>
   <bibl>Arngart, O. S., ‘Some aspects of the relation between the English and the Danish element in the Danelaw’,<i>Studia Neophilologica</i>, 20 (1948), 73–87.</bibl>
   <bibl>Barnwell, P. S., ‘“Hlafeata, ceorl, hid and scir”: Celtic, Roman or Germanic?’,<i>Anglo-Saxon Studies in Archaeology &amp; History</i>, 9 (1996), 53–62.</bibl>
   <bibl>Fellows Jensen, G., ‘Of Danes – and thanes – and Domesday Book’, in Wood, I. N., and Lund, N. (eds.),People and Places in Northern Europe, 500–1600: Essays in Honour of Peter Hayes Sawyer(Woodbridge, 1991), pp. 107–21.</bibl>
   <bibl>Garnett, G., ‘“Franci et Angli”: the legal distinctions between peoples after the Conquest’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 8 (1985), 109–37.</bibl>
   <bibl>Grimmer, M., ‘Britons in Early Wessex: the evidence of the Law Code of Ine’, in Higham, N. J. (ed.),<i>Britons in Anglo-Saxon England</i>(Publications of the Manchester Centre for Anglo-Saxon Studies, 7, Woodbridge, 2007), pp. 102–14.</bibl>
   <bibl>Grimmer, M., ‘Britons and Saxons in pre-Viking Wessex: reflections on the Law 77 of King Ine’,<i>Parergon</i>, 19 (2002), 1–17.</bibl>
   <bibl>Routledge, R., ‘The legal status of the Jews in England 1190–1790’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 3 (1982), 91–124.</bibl>
   <bibl>Watt, J. A., ‘The Jews, the law, and the church: the concept of Jewish serfdom in thirteenth-century England’, in Wood, D. (ed.),The Church and Sovereignty, c.590–1918: Essays in Honour of Michael Wilks(Studies in Church History, Subsidia, 9, Oxford, 1991), pp. 153–72.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘The<i>Leges Barbarorum</i>: law and ethnicity in the post-Roman west’, in Goetz, H.-W.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Regna and Gentes: the Relationship between Late Antique and Early Medieval Peoples and Kingdoms in the Transformation of the Roman World</i>(Transformation of the Roman World, 13, Leiden, 2003), pp. 21–53.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Forest law</bibl>
   <bibl>Amt, E., ‘The forest regard of 1155’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 2 (1990), 189–95.</bibl>
   <bibl>Birrell, J., ‘Common rights in the medieval forest: disputes and conflicts in the thirteenth century’,<i>Past &amp; Present</i>, 117 (1987), 22–49.</bibl>
   <bibl>Crook, D., ‘The exemption of Nottingham from the forest laws in the twelfth and thirteenth centuries’,<i>Transactions of the Thoroton Society of Nottinghamshire</i>, 109 (2005), 69–73.</bibl>
   <bibl>Crook, D., ‘The records of forest eyres in the Public Record Office, 1179 to 1670’,<i>Journal of the Society of Archivists</i>, 17 (1996), 183–93.</bibl>
   <bibl>Marvin, W. P.,<i>Hunting Law and Ritual in Medieval English Literature</i>(Cambridge, 2006).</bibl>
   <bibl>Young, C. R.,<i>The</i>
      <i>Royal Forests of Medieval England</i>(Leicester, 1979).</bibl>
   <bibl>Young, C. R., ‘Conservation policies in the royal forests of medieval England’,Albion, 10 (1978), 95–103.</bibl>
   <bibl>Young, C. R., ‘English royal forests under the Angevin kings’,<i>Journal of British Studies</i>, 12 (1972), 1–14.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Glanvill</bibl>
   <bibl>Butler, P. T. T., ‘Who wrote Glanville?’,<i>Journal of the Butler Society</i>, 3 (1994), 500–1.</bibl>
   <bibl>Falls, J. S., ‘Ranulf de Granville’s formative years<i>c</i>.1120–79: the family background and his ascent to the justiciarship’,<i>Mediaeval Studies</i>, 40 (1978), 312–27.</bibl>
   <bibl>Russell, J. C., ‘Ranulf de Glanville’, in Russell, J. C. (ed.),Twelfth Century Studies(New York, 1978), pp. 126–41.</bibl>
   <bibl>Tullis, S., ‘Glanvill continued: a reassessment’, in Lewis, A. D. E.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Law in the City: Proceedings of the Seventeenth British Legal History Conference, London, 2005</i>(Dublin, 2007), pp. 15–23.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘Who was the author of Glanvill? Reflections on the education of Henry II’s common lawyers’,<i>Law and History Review</i>, 8 (1990), 97–127.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V.,<i>The English Judiciary in the Age of Glanvill and Bracton, c.1176–1239</i>(Cambridge, 1985).</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Land and tenure</bibl>
   <bibl>Bailey, S. J., ‘Warranties of land in the reign of Richard I’,<i>Cambridge Law Journal</i>, 9 (1946), 192–209.</bibl>
   <bibl>Bates, D., ‘The land pleas of William I’s reign: Penenden Heath revisited’,<i>Bulletin of the Institute of Historical Research</i>, 51 (1978), 1–19.</bibl>
   <bibl>Buckstaff, G., ‘Married women’s property in Anglo-Saxon and Anglo-Norman law and the origin of the common law dower’,<i>Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Sciences</i>, 4 (1893–4), 233–64.</bibl>
   <bibl>Cheney, M., ‘“Possessio/proprietas” in ecclesiastical courts in mid twelfth-century England’, in Garnett, G., and Hudson, J. (eds.),Law and Government in Medieval England and Normandy: Essays in Honour of Sir James Holt(Cambridge, 1994), pp. 245–54.</bibl>
   <bibl>Douglas, A. W., ‘Tenure in<i>elemosina</i>: origins and establishment in twelfth-century England’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 24 (1980), 95–132.</bibl>
   <bibl>Douglas, A. W., ‘Frankalmoin and the jurisdictional immunity: Maitland revisited’,<i>Speculum</i>, 53 (1978), 26–48.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hart, C. J. R., ‘The hide, the carucate and the ploughland’, in Hart, C. J. R. (ed.),The Danelaw(London, 1992), pp. 289–335.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J., ‘Anglo-Norman land law and the origins of property’, in Garnett, G., and Hudson, J. (eds.),Law and Government in Medieval England and Normandy: Essays in Honour of Sir James Holt(Cambridge, 1994), pp. 198–222.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J.,<i>Land, Law and Lordship in Anglo-Norman England</i>(Oxford, 1994).<i/>
   </bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J., ‘Life-grants and the development of inheritance in Anglo-Norman England’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 12 (1989), 67–80.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘“No register of title”: the Domesday inquest and land adjudication’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 9 (1986), 128–41.</bibl>
   <bibl>Ibbetson, D. J., ‘From property to contract: the transformation of sale in the middle ages’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 13 (1992), 1–22.</bibl>
   <bibl>Kennedy, A. G., ‘Disputes about<i>bocland</i>: the forum for their adjudication’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 14 (1985), 175–95.</bibl>
   <bibl>King, E., ‘The tenurial crisis of the early twelfth century’,<i>Past &amp; Present</i>, 65 (1974), 110–17.</bibl>
   <bibl>Loyn, H. R., ‘The hundred in England in the tenth and early eleventh centuries’, in Hearder, H., and Loyn, H. R. (eds.),<i>British Government and Administration: Studies Presented to S. B. Chrimes</i>(Cardiff, 1974), pp. 1–15.</bibl>
   <bibl>McGovern, J. F., ‘The hide and related land-tenure concepts in Anglo-Saxon England, AD 700–1100’,<i>Traditio</i>, 28 (1972), 101–18.</bibl>
   <bibl>McGovern, J. F., ‘The meaning of ‘Gesette land’ in Anglo-Saxon land tenure’,<i>Speculum</i>, 46 (1971), 589–96.</bibl>
   <bibl>Meyer, M. A., ‘Land charters and the legal position of Anglo-Saxon women’, in Kanner, B. (ed.),The Women of England from Anglo-Saxon Times to the Present: Interpretive Bibliographical Essays(London, 1980), pp. 57–82.</bibl>
   <bibl>Postles, D., ‘Tenure in frankalmoign and knight service in twelfth-century England: interpretation of the charters’,<i>Journal of the Society of Archivists</i>, 13 (1992), 18–28.</bibl>
   <bibl>Roffe, D. R., ‘From thegnage to barony: sake and soke, title and tenants-in-chief’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 12 (1989), 157–76.</bibl>
   <bibl>Tabuteau, E. Z.,<i>Transfers of Property in Eleventh-Century Norman Law</i>(Chapel Hill, NC,1988).</bibl>
   <bibl>Tate, J. C., ‘Ownership and possession in the early common law’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 48 (2006), 280–313.</bibl>
   <bibl>Thorn, F. R., ‘Hundreds and wapentakes’, in Williams, A., and Erskine, R. W. H. (eds.),The Leicestershire Domesday(Alecto County Edition of Domesday Book, 16,London,1990), pp. 22–30.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, G. J., ‘Bookland and folkland’, in Edwards, J. G., Galbraith, V. H.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Historical Essays in Honour of James Tait</i>(Manchester, 1933), pp. 357–86.</bibl>
   <bibl>Williams, A., ‘How land was held before and after the Norman Conquest’, in Williams, A. (ed.),Domesday Book Studies(Alecto county edition of Domesday Book, 3,London,1987), pp. 37–8.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Magna Carta</bibl>
   <bibl>Clanchy, M. T., ‘Magna Carta, clause 34’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 79 (1964), 542–8.</bibl>
   <bibl>Galbraith, V. H., ‘A draft of Magna Carta (1215)’,<i>Proceedings of the British Academy</i>, 53 (1967), 345–60.</bibl>
   <bibl>Holt, J. C.,<i>Magna Carta</i>(2nd edn., Cambridge, 1992).</bibl>
   <bibl>Hurnard, N. D., ‘Magna Carta, clause 34’, in Hunt, R. W.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Studies in Medieval History presented to Frederick Maurice Powicke</i>(Oxford, 1948), pp. 157–79.</bibl>
   <bibl>Jones, J. A. P.,<i>King John and Magna Carta</i>(London, 1971).</bibl>
   <bibl>McIlwain, C. H., ‘Magna Carta and common law’, in Malden, H. E. (ed.),<i>Magna Carta Commemoration Essays</i>(London, 1917), pp. 122-79.</bibl>
   <bibl>Powicke, F. M., ‘Per iudicium parium vel per legem terrae’, in Malden, H. E. (ed.),<i>Magna Carta Commemoration Essays</i>(London, 1917), pp. 96-121.</bibl>
   <bibl>Smith, J. B., ‘Magna Carta and the charters of the Welsh princes’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 99 (1984), 344–62.</bibl>
   <bibl>Vinogradoff, P. G., ‘Magna Carta, c. 39: nullus liber homo, etc.’, in Malden, H. E. (ed.),<i>Magna Carta Commemoration Essays</i>(London, 1917).</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Marriage</bibl>
   <bibl>Brooke, C. N. L., ‘Marriage and society in the central middle ages’, in Outhwaite, R. B. (ed.),Marriage and Society: Studies in the Social History of Marriage(London, 1981), pp. 17–34.</bibl>
   <bibl>Buckstaff, G., ‘Married women’s property in Anglo-Saxon and Anglo-Norman law and the origin of the common law dower’,<i>Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Sciences</i>, 4 (1893–4), 233–64.</bibl>
   <bibl>Clanchy, M. T., ‘Law and love in the middle ages’, in Bossy, J. A. (ed.),<i>Disputes and Settlements: Law and Human Relations in the West</i>(Cambridge, 1983), pp. 47–67.</bibl>
   <bibl>Engdahl, D. E., ‘English marriage conflicts law before the time of Bracton’,<i>American Journal of Comparative Law</i>, 15 (1966–7), 109–35.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hill, R. M. T., ‘Marriage in seventh-century England’, in King, M. H., and Stevens, W. M. (ed.),Saints, Scholars and Heroes: Studies in Medieval Culture in Honour of Charles W. Jones(2 vols.,Collegeville, MI, 1979), vol. 1, 67–76.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘The early Kentish “divorce laws”: a reconsideration of Æthelberht, chs. 79 and 80’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 23 (1994), 19–34.</bibl>
   <bibl>Klinck, A. L., ‘“To have and to hold”: the bridewealth of wives and the<i>mund</i>of widows in Anglo-Saxon England’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 51 (2007), 231–45.</bibl>
   <bibl>Loengard, J. S., ‘“Of the gift of her husband”: English dower and its consequences in the year 1200’, in Kirshner, J., and Wemple, S. (eds.),Women of the Medieval World:Essays in Honor of John H. Mundy(Oxford, 1985), pp. 215–55.</bibl>
   <bibl>Richardson, H. G., ‘The marriage of Isabelle of Angoulême: a problem of canon law’, in Forchielli, J., and Stickler, A. M. (eds.),<i>Studia Gratiana post octava decreti saecularia auctore consilio commemorationi Gratianae Instruendae edita</i>(Collectanea historiae juris canonici, 11, Rome, 1967), pp. 397–423.</bibl>
   <bibl>Rolker, C., ‘Kings, bishops and incest: extension and subversion of the ecclesiastical marriage jurisdiction around 1100’,Studies in Church History, 43 (2007), 159–68.</bibl>
   <bibl>Sheehan, M. M., ‘Theory and practice: marriage of the unfree and the poor in medieval society’,<i>Mediaeval Studies</i>, 50 (1988), 458–87.</bibl>
   <bibl>Walker, S. S., ‘Free consent and marriage of feudal wards in medieval England’,<i>Journal of Medieval History</i>, 8 (1982), 123–34.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Money and mints</bibl>
   <bibl>Blackburn, M. A. S., ‘Mints,<i>burhs</i>, and the Grately Code, cap. 14.2’, in Hill, D., and Rumble, A. R. (eds.),The Defence of Wessex: the Burghal Hidage and Anglo-Saxon Fortifications(Manchester, 1996), pp. 160–75.</bibl>
   <bibl>Gillingham, J., ‘“The most precious jewel in the English crown”: levels of Danegeld and Heregeld in the early eleventh century’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 104 (1989), 373–84.</bibl>
   <bibl>Kinsey, R. S., ‘Anglo-Saxon law and practice relating to mints and moneyers, with particular reference to the mints of Chichester, London, Dover, and Northampton, and the moneyer(s) Cynsige or Kinsey’,<i>British Numismatic Journal</i>, 3rd ser., 9 (1959 for 1958), 12–50.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘Danegeld and Heregeld once more’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 105 (1990), 951–61.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘“Those stories look true”: levels of taxation in the reigns of Aethelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 104 (1989), 385–406.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘The collection of Danegeld and Heregeld in the reigns of Aethelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 99 (1984), 721–38.</bibl>
   <bibl>Screen, E., ‘Anglo-Saxon law and numismatics: a reassessment in the light of Patrick Wormald’s<i>The Making of English Law</i>’,<i>British Numismatic Journal</i>, 77 (2007), 150–72.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stack, G., ‘A lost law of Henry II: the Assize of Oxford and monetary reform’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 16 (2006 for 2005), 95–103.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Ordeals and judicial duels</bibl>
   <bibl>Bartlett, R.,<i>Trial by Fire and Water: the Medieval Judicial Ordeal</i>(Oxford, 1986).</bibl>
   <bibl>Hyams, P. R., ‘Trial by ordeal: the key to proof in the early common law’, in Green, M. S. A.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),On the Laws and Customs of England: Essays in Honor of Samuel E. Thorne(Chapel Hill, NC, 1981), pp. 90–126.</bibl>
   <bibl>Larratt Keefer, S., ‘<i>Donne se cirlisca man ordales weddigeð</i>: the Anglo-Saxon lay ordeal’, in Baxter, S., Karkov, C.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Early Medieval Studies in Memory of Patrick Wormald</i>(Farnham, 2009), pp. 353–67.</bibl>
   <bibl>Martindale, J., ‘Between law and politics: the judicial duel under the Angevin Kings (mid-twelfth century to 1204)’, in Stafford, P.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Law, Laity and Solidarities: Essays in Honour of Susan Reynolds</i>(Manchester, 2001), pp. 116–49.</bibl>
   <bibl>Niles, J. D., ‘Trial by ordeal in Anglo-Saxon England: what’s the problem with barley?’, in Baxter, S., Karkov, C.,<i>et al.</i>(eds.),<i>Early Medieval Studies in Memory of Patrick Wormald</i>(Farnham, 2009), pp. 369–82.</bibl>
   <bibl>Russell, M. J., ‘Trial by battle and the writ of right; trial by battle and the appeals of felony’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 1 (1980), 111–64.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Peace</bibl>
   <bibl>Colman, R. V., ‘Domestic peace and public order in Anglo-Saxon law’, in Woods, J. D., and Pelteret, D. A. E. (eds.),<i>The Anglo-Saxons: Synthesis and Achievement</i>(Waterloo, 1985), pp. 49–61.</bibl>
   <bibl>Fordham, M., ‘Peacekeeping and order on the Anglo-Welsh frontier in the early tenth century’,<i>Midland History</i>, 32 (2007), 1–18.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lund, N., ‘Peace and non-peace in the Viking age: Ottar in Biarmaland, the Rus in Byzantium and Danes and Norwegians in England’, in Knirk, J. E. (ed.),<i>Proceedings of the Tenth Viking Congress</i>(Oslo, 1987), pp. 255–69.</bibl>
   <bibl>O’Brien, B.,<i>God’s Peace and King’s Peace: the Laws of Edward the Confessor</i>(Philadelphia, PA, 1999).</bibl>
   <bibl>Ratcliffe, R., ‘Keeping the peace’,<i>Ancestors</i>, 17 (2003).</bibl>
   <bibl>Weber, J. K., ‘The king’s peace: a comparative study’,<i>Journal of Legal History</i>, 10 (1989), 135–60.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wormald, P., ‘<i>Inter cetera bona</i>–<i>genti suae</i>: law-making and peace-keeping in the earliest English kingdoms’,<i>Settimane dello studio del centro italiano di studi sull’alto medioevo</i>, 42 (1995), 963–93.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Succession and inheritance</bibl>
   <bibl>Beckerman, J. S., ‘Succession in Normandy, 1087, and in England, 1066: the role of testamentary custom’,<i>Speculum</i>, 47 (1972), 258–60.</bibl>
   <bibl>Drout, M. D.C., ‘Blood and deeds: the inheritance systems inBeowulf’,Studies in Philology, 104 (2007), 199–226.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hudson, J., ‘Life-grants and the development of inheritance in Anglo-Norman England’,<i>Anglo-Norman Studies</i>, 12 (1989), 67–80.</bibl>
   <bibl>Tabuteau, E. Z., ‘The role of law in the succession to Normandy and England, 1087’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 3 (1993 for 1991), 141–69.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘Exercise of the king’s will in inheritance of baronies: the example of King John and William Briwerre’,<i>Albion</i>, 22 (1990), 383–401.</bibl>
   <bibl>Turner, R. V., ‘The Mandeville inheritance, 1189–1236: its legal, political, and social context’,<i>Haskins Society Journal</i>, 1 (1989), 147–72.</bibl>
   <bibl>Waugh, S. L., ‘Women’s inheritance and the growth of bureaucratic monarchy in twelfth- and thirteenth-century England’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 34 (1990), 71–92.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Towns and trade</bibl>
   <bibl>Brooke, C. N. L., ‘Henry’s Charter for the City of London’,<i>Journal of the Society of Archivists</i>, 4 (1973), 558–78.</bibl>
   <bibl>Haslam, J., ‘Market and fortress in England in the reign of Offa’,<i>World Archaeology</i>, 19 (1987), 76–93.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lloyd, T. H.,<i>Alien Merchants in England in the High Middle Ages</i>(Brighton, 1982).</bibl>
   <bibl>Richardson, H. G., ‘Henry I’s Charter to London’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 42 (1927), 80–7.</bibl>
   <bibl>Russell, J. C., ‘The date of Henry I’s Charter to London’, in Russell, J. C. (ed.),Twelfth Century Studies(New York, 1978), pp. 94–102.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Women and widows</bibl>
   <bibl>Alamichel, M.-F.,<i>Widows in Anglo-Saxon and Medieval Britain</i>(Oxford, 2008).</bibl>
   <bibl>Colman, R. V., ‘“Under her own lock and key”: women’s position in early medieval law and society’, in Birks, P. B. H. (ed.),The Life of the Law: Proceedings of the Tenth British Legal History Conference, Oxford, 1991(London, 1993), pp. 45–58.</bibl>
   <bibl>Crick, J. C., ‘Men, women and widows: widowhood in pre-Conquest England’, in Cavallo, S., and Warner, L. (eds.),Widowhood in Medieval and Early Modern Europe(Harlow, 1999), pp. 24–36.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hollis, S., ‘“The protection of God and the king”: Wulfstan’s legislation on widows’, in Townend, M. (ed.),<i>Wulfstan, Archbishop of York: the Proceedings of the Second Alcuin Conference</i>(Studies in the Early Middle Ages, 10, Turnhout, 2004), pp. 443–60.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘Women and the law in seventh-century England’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 51 (2007), 207–30.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘Two Kentish laws concerning women: a new reading of Æthelberht 73 and 74’,<i>Anglia: Zeitschrift für englische Philologie</i>, 119 (2001), 554–78.</bibl>
   <bibl>Hough, C., ‘The early Kentish “divorce laws”: a reconsideration of Æthelberht, chs. 79 and 80’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 23 (1994), 19–34.</bibl>
   <bibl>Kittel, M. R., ‘Women under the law in medieval England, 1066–1485’, in Kanner, B. (ed.),The Women of England from Anglo-Saxon Times to the Present: Interpretive Bibliographical Essays(London, 1980), pp. 124–37.</bibl>
   <bibl>Klinck, A. L., ‘“To have and to hold”: the bridewealth of wives and the<i>mund</i>of widows in Anglo-Saxon England’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 51 (2007), 231–45.</bibl>
   <bibl>Klinck, A. L., ‘Anglo-Saxon women and the law’,<i>Journal of Medieval History</i>, 8 (1982), 107–21.</bibl>
   <bibl>Loengard, J. S., ‘“Of the gift of her husband”: English dower and its consequences in the year 1200’, in Kirshner, J., and Wemple, S. (eds.),Women of the Medieval World:Essays in Honor of John H. Mundy(Oxford, 1985), pp. 215–55.</bibl>
   <bibl>Meyer, M. A., ‘Land charters and the legal position of Anglo-Saxon women’, in Kanner, B. (ed.),The Women of England from Anglo-Saxon Times to the Present: Interpretive Bibliographical Essays(London, 1980), pp. 57–82.</bibl>
   <bibl>Richards, M. P., and Stanfield, B. J., ‘Concepts of Anglo-Saxon women in the laws’, in Damico, H., and Olsen, A. H. (eds.),<i>New Readings on Women in Old English Literature</i>(Bloomington, ID, 1990), pp. 89–99.</bibl>
   <bibl>Rivers, T. J., ‘Adultery in early Anglo-Saxon society: Æthelberht 31 in comparison with continental Germanic law’,<i>Anglo-Saxon England</i>, 20 (1991), 19–25.</bibl>
   <bibl>Rivers, T. J., ‘Widows’ rights in Anglo-Saxon law’,<i>American Journal of Legal History</i>, 19 (1975), 208–15.</bibl>
   <bibl>Waugh, S. L., ‘Women’s inheritance and the growth of bureaucratic monarchy in twelfth- and thirteenth-century England’,<i>Nottingham Mediaeval Studies</i>, 34 (1990), 71–92.</bibl>
   <bibl>Wolf, G.,‘Aethelfled von Mercia und ottonische “dominae”: zun Rechtscharakter frühmittelalterlicher Frauenherrschaft’,Zeitschrift der Savigny-Stiftung für Rechtsgeschichte.<i>Germanistische Abteilung</i>, 111 (1994), 525–35.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
   <bibl>Wulfstan</bibl>
   <bibl>Cross, J. E., and Hamer, A. (eds.),<i>Wulfstan’s Canon Law Collection</i>(Anglo-Saxon Texts, 1, Woodbridge, 1999).</bibl>
   <bibl>Hollis, S., ‘“The protection of God and the king”: Wulfstan’s legislation on widows’, in Townend, M. (ed.),<i>Wulfstan, Archbishop of York: the Proceedings of the Second Alcuin Conference</i>(Studies in the Early Middle Ages, 10, Turnhout, 2004), pp. 443–60.</bibl>
   <bibl>Lawson, M. K., ‘Archbishop Wulfstan and the homiletic element in the Laws of Æthelred II and Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 107 (1992), 565–86.</bibl>
   <bibl>Stanley, E. G., ‘Wulfstan and Ælfric: “the true difference between the law and the gospel”’, in Townend, M. (ed.),<i>Wulfstan, Archbishop of York: the Proceedings of the Second Alcuin Conference</i>(Studies in the Early Middle Ages, 10, Turnhout, 2004), pp. 429–41.</bibl>
   <bibl>Whitelock, D., ‘Wulfstan Cantor and Anglo-Saxon law’, in Orrick, A. H. (ed.),<i>Nordica et Anglica: Studies in Honor of Stefán Ginarsson</i>(The Hague, 1968), pp. 83–92.</bibl>
   <bibl>Whitelock, D., ‘Wulfstan’s authorship of Cnut’s laws’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 70 (1955), 72–85.</bibl>
   <bibl>Whitelock, D., ‘Wulfstan and the Laws of Cnut’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 63 (1948), 433–52.</bibl>
   <bibl>Whitelock, D., ‘Wulfstan and the so-called Laws of Edward and Guthrum’,<i>English Historical Review</i>, 56 (1941), 1–21.</bibl>
   <bibl/>
</listBibl>
